<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Rounded Globe</title>
 <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/"/>
 <updated>2016-01-10T08:53:02+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog</id>
 
 <author>
   <name>Rounded Globe</name>
   <email>roundedglobe@gmail.com</email>
 
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Chaucer Goes To The Golden Horde</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/chaucer-goes-to-the-golden-horde/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/chaucer-goes-to-the-golden-horde</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Chaucer set his &lt;em&gt;Squire’s Tale&lt;/em&gt; at ‘Sarray, in the land of Tartarye’ – that is, Saray, city of the Golden Horde Mongols, Jochi’s &lt;em&gt;ulus&lt;/em&gt;, above the Black and Caspian Seas. What did Chaucer know or care about a Tartar khan at Saray and his court?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Squire’s Tale&lt;/em&gt;, as a romance, has been despised in the past; people have said it’s unfinished either because Chaucer had too much discrimination to go on or because the other Canterbury pilgrims stopped the squire’s drivel. You can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.librarius.com/cantales.htm&quot;&gt;read it yourself&lt;/a&gt; and judge. If you like medieval romances (adventure tales, with fantastic happenings, errant knights and wandering plots), there’s nothing wrong with it. It is unfinished, to the point that it’s only just begun. We are left with the khan’s daughter, gifted with a ‘quaint ring’ that lets her understand the talk of birds, having listened to the confession of a she-falcon, intent on self-harm, who has been seduced and left for a rival; the rest of the court are still asleep, after a grand feast whereat was given to the khan a flying horse of brass, that transports you anywhere when you tweak its ears. Nobody knows what happened next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be dismissed as a mishmash of wild marvels ‘for those who like that sort of thing’. Who knew that the &lt;em&gt;Squire’s Tale&lt;/em&gt; had historical value? Carmel Jordan told the world in 1987 when she consulted archaeological work written in Russian, and saw that the Golden Horde was as spectacular as Chaucer describes (you can take &lt;a href=&quot;http://ibnbattuta.berkeley.edu/6goldenhorde.html&quot;&gt;a little trip&lt;/a&gt; with Ibn Battuta, to visit the khan in his gold-tiled tent in 1332-3). The setting, at least, wasn’t wild imagination; and furthermore, she suggests that every marvel had its real-life kick-off: the bronze horse, for instance, might have been put into Chaucer’s head by gift steeds that caused a stir at Mongol courts for their unusual size and general foreign glamour. The khans had a fascination with contrivances, too, that might inspire Chaucer’s magical ornamentation: the ingenious silver tree that dispensed drinks at Karakorum had its counterpart in Saray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaucer, unfortunately, never set foot in Saray himself or indeed the Golden Horde. How did he come to be informed? In the latter 13th and the 14th centuries, near the end of which the &lt;em&gt;Squire’s Tale&lt;/em&gt; was written, the khans of Saray and the Italian merchant republics operated in a symbiosis, for an unprecedented age of trade. Genoese, above Venetians, won the major part of the Black Sea trade, and moved with confidence in the Mongol world. Genoa also outstripped other Italian cities in trade relations with England. Chaucer took part in a delegation to Genoa for trade discussions in 1372-3; subsequently he was employed in Customs for the port of London. It is agreed he had ample opportunity, in diplomatic and commercial circles, to hear from Genoese their tales of Saray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently Michael Murrin has written a great book on &lt;em&gt;Trade and Romance&lt;/em&gt;: how romance, first turned by Marco Polo’s travels, changed from a ‘Celtic fantastic’ to a ‘marvelous real’ – set in Asia, and driven not by the interests of aristocratic fighting men, although these remain the heroes of romance, but by the adventurous activities of merchants. He posits a dual audience for such romances as the Squire’s Tale, both upper class and those who live by commerce. It is the case that fighting men didn’t visit Saray: merchants did (not that these merchants weren’t up for a fight). Merchants went further, and saw things undreamt of by knights. The popular romances followed in their steps – but doing this, they lost status, and were trivialised, too, in the scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m fascinated by Chaucer’s trip of the imagination to Saray, and later adventures too of European romancers in the Mongol world. More to come on my own blog, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amgalant.com/&quot;&gt;Amgalant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Main works consulted:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virgil Ciocîltan, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brill.com/mongols-and-black-sea-trade-thirteenth-and-fourteenth-centuries&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Mongols and the Black Sea Trade in the Thirteenth and Fourteenth Centuries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, translated by Samuel Willcocks, Leiden, Brill, 2012.&lt;br&gt;
Carmel Jordan, ‘Soviet Archeology and the Setting of the Squire’s Tale’, &lt;em&gt;The Chaucer Review&lt;/em&gt;, volume 22, issue 2, 1987, pp. 128-9.&lt;br&gt;
Michael Murrin, &lt;a href=&quot;http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/T/bo16552205.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trade and Romance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Chicago &amp;amp; London, University of Chicago Press, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Changing Faces Of Britain&#39;s Natives</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/changing-faces-of-britain's-natives/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/changing-faces-of-britain's-natives</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Late-Victorian histories of the English began in the woods of Schleswig, before the migration to the British Isles. But around 1900 historians decided that English history proper should begin with the foundation of the modern state in the fourteenth century. What came before was deemed not only barbarous but insufficiently documented. The story of ancient Britain, and of the peoples who settled it, was left to a motley crew of archaeologists, folklorists, philologists and, increasingly, writers of fiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cook1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Picture from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/ourislandstoryhi00marsuoft&quot;&gt;Our Island Story. A History of England for Boys and Girls&lt;/a&gt;, by H.E. Marshall, illustration by A.S. Forrester (London, 1905).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first section of my Rounded Globe essay on &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.com/book/54f6fe79648a590459746be1/J.R.R.%20Tolkien&amp;#x27;s%20Lost%20English%20Mythology&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;J.R.R. Tolkien&amp;#39;s Lost English Mythology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#39;ve discussed some facets of the early twentieth-century search for the ancient English; in this post I track the changing face of Britain’s natives. The picture above depicts a sort of ancient ‘close encounters’ moment: native Britons watch the arrival of the Roman fleet of Julius Caesar. This captures the conventional Victorian image of the Romans bringing civilization to a savage island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare the primitive Britons above, barefoot and attired in rude animal skins, with the blond giants below. Although this second picture was published earlier, it embodies a newer kind of historical thinking. These iron-age warriors are still Britons, but they are no longer natives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cook2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Picture from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/bericthebriton00hentrich&quot;&gt;Beric the Briton. A Story of the Roman Invasion&lt;/a&gt;, by G.A. Henty, illustrator unknown (London, 1893).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For much of the nineteenth century it was assumed that Britain had been settled for only a few generations before the coming of the Romans. But this view became untenable after 1877 and the publication of Canon William Greenwell’s &lt;em&gt;British Barrows&lt;/em&gt;. From his meticulous and extensive archaeological excavations, Greenwell drew the conclusion that prehistoric long barrows were not only older than round barrows, but had been built by a different people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cook3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Image from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/britishbarrowsre00gree&quot;&gt;British Barrows. A record of the examination of the sepulchral mounds in various parts of England&lt;/a&gt;, by W. Greenwell (Oxford, 1877).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Greenwell it was generally accepted that the Celtic-speaking Britons, the supposed makers of the round barrows, had intruded upon an earlier population. The result was the rehabilitation of the Britons: no longer the passive victims of history, conquered and pushed aside by more vigorous peoples, the Britons became invading immigrants in their own right – ancient barbarians, maybe, yet virtuous and worthy ancestors for the modern British. In the caption of the second picture above the leading Briton declares: ‘Tell Suetonius that we scorn his mercy and will die as we have lived, free men.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who, then, were the newly discovered natives? With precious little archaeological or philological evidence to work with, scholars turned to fairy tales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1900 John Rhys, the first Oxford Professor of Celtic, delivered the presidential address to the Anthropology section of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/reportofbritisha00scie&quot;&gt;British Association for the Advancement of Science&lt;/a&gt;. His chosen theme was the value of folk tales for the study of the ancient past, and he argued that behind the ‘rabble of divinities and demons’ who disport themselves in Celtic folklore it is possible to discern the succession of peoples who have inhabited the British Isles. Welsh fairy stories, according to Rhys, contained dim memories of the native population encountered by the first Celtic-speaking intruders. The real ‘little people’, he inferred, had been ‘a small swarthy population of mound-dwellers, of an unwarlike disposition... and living underground’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cook4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Picture from the cover of &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/watcherbythresho00buchuoft&quot;&gt;John Buchan’s The Watcher by the Threshold&lt;/a&gt; (London, 1902).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhys’ ideas seem to have sparked the imagination of a couple of young minds. John Buchan went up to Oxford in 1895. His short story ‘No-Man’s-Land’, which appeared in print seven years later, tells the dreadful story of an Oxford scholar of Northern Antiquities (like Rhys perhaps, or one of his students), who holidays in the remote Highlands of Scotland, where he encounters – and is  taken captive by – ‘the Hidden People’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then suddenly in the hollow trough of mist before me... there appeared a figure. It was little and squat and dark; naked, apparently, but so rough with hair that it wore the appearance of a skin-covering... in its face and eyes there seemed to lurk an elder world of mystery and barbarism, a troll-like life which was too horrible for words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While captive in their ‘hill refuge’ the Oxford scholar hears harsh words directed at the British invader, bitter curses for the Saxon stranger; and he glimpses ‘a morbid hideous existence’ preserved for centuries by these relics of a nameless past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchan’s natives are the complete antithesis of the modern British subject; a sort of primitive Hyde to the modern Dr. Jekyll. One can perhaps discern a post-WWII twist to this fable in &lt;em&gt;The Inheritors&lt;/em&gt;, the 1955 novel by William Golding (who incidentally attended the same Oxford college as Buchan). In Golding’s story the original dwellers of the land have become Neanderthals – a separate species to modern humans. But in contrast to Buchan, Golding represents these natives as a peaceful if queer-thinking folk; it is the human intruders who are violent and frightening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchan’s portrayal of Britain’s ancient folk as radically different to the modern population of the British Isles made for a good story; but it did not reflect an Edwardian scholarly consensus that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; newcomers to Britain had interbred with those already settled on the land. Far from being a separate species, scholars believed that much native blood flows through the veins of the inhabitants of modern Britain (the same kind of idea is now put in terms of DNA). An Englishman, a Scotsman, or a Welshmen who meets one of the forgotten little people is quite possibly discovering but a smaller version of himself. And if such encounters have today become rather rare in the fields and hedgerows of Britain, this is a familiar enough experience to many readers of J.R.R. Tolkien’s classic children’s story of 1937, &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hobbits are a homely depiction of Britain’s natives. Tolkien tells us that they are a ‘little people’, who today ‘have become rare and shy of the Big People, as they call us’. But once upon a time, ‘long ago in the quiet of the world, when there was less noise and more green’, hobbits were ‘numerous and prosperous’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going up to Oxford in 1911, Tolkien as an undergraduate probably attended Rhys’ lectures; later, in a short essay of 1932, we find him engaging carefully with his scholarship. And it seems that Tolkien had read the Professor of Celtic’s 1900 presidential address. At one point in this lecture Rhys discusses certain ‘underground – or partially underground – habitations’ that, he believed, had been home to Britain’s natives. These abodes, he explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;appear from the outside like hillocks covered with grass, so as presumably not to attract attention... But one of the most remarkable things about them is the fact that the cells or apartments into which they are divided are frequently so small that their inmates must have been of very short stature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if Tolkien first stumbled upon a hobbit hole whilst reading Rhys’ lecture, it seems likely that his imagination drew also upon Buchan’s depiction of Britain’s natives as subhuman trolls. Certainly, John Buchan was one of Tolkien’s favourite authors. Of course, Bilbo’s hole under the hill is snug and comfortable; the encounter with a ‘hideous existence’ within a ‘hill refuge’ described by Buchan finds its counterpart, not at Bag End, but in that cave deep within the Misty Mountains into which had wormed his way, long ages ago, ‘a small slimy creature’ called Gollum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: ‘Bag End’, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/cwagner33/16412701584/in/photolist-r1konw-f1vrhZ-r9T7na-gSUGYy-fmydgt-oFniqm-qXCt91-eTWhEj-gQcA7v-dW2JCm-nkC5Az-nnouXK-dW2ydC-dTYvrS-qwwRR-rV3eUY-kwR9Kt-78p8QM-kz4UY4-meQa1g-AYZ1kw-7p1Q5Z-rNagXL-5Dke6x-qJhsWF-2bFs5Y-dBstuz-dBxTow-rXvrG5-o6h9pM-dW2C1A-33BvLu-bxVL-ooUeXN-dMMizo-gcABdA-gcxSvr-rXyuCP-rFbrFe-rPZsi5-rhsYc-5vDr9z-gLP9h9-4aysoZ-qFY2N4-rmbW7C-qX9auA-qXdT6B-qZsMSU-nJM8Qs&quot;&gt;Christopher Wagner&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Can&#39;t Disrupt This</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/can't-disrupt-this/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/can't-disrupt-this</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Elsevier and the 25.2 Billion Dollar A Year Academic Publishing Business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scribd.com/doc/292346391/Forbes-Elsevier-1995&quot;&gt;December 18, 1995&lt;/a&gt;), Forbes predicted academic publisher Elsevier’s relevancy and life in the digital age to be short lived. In an article entitled “The internet’s first victim,” journalist John Hayes highlights the technological imperative coming toward the academic publisher’s profit margin with the growing internet culture and said, “Cost-cutting librarians and computer-literate professors are bypassing academic journals — bad news for Elsevier.” After publication of the article, investors seemed to heed Hayes’s rationale for Elsevier’s impeding demise. Elsevier stock fell 7% in two days to $26 a share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the smoke settles twenty years later, one of the clear winners on this longitudinal timeline of innovation is the very firm that investors, journalists, and forecasters wrote off early as a casualty to digital evolution: Elsevier. Perhaps to the chagrin of many academics, the publisher has actually not been bruised nor battered. In fact, the publisher’s health is stronger than ever. As of 2015, the academic publishing market that Elsevier leads has an annual revenue of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stm-assoc.org/2015_02_20_STM_Report_2015.pdf&quot;&gt;$25.2 billion&lt;/a&gt;. According to its 2013 financials &lt;a href=&quot;http://poeticeconomics.blogspot.co.il/2014/03/elsevier-stm-publishing-profits-rise-to.html&quot;&gt;Elsevier&lt;/a&gt; had a higher percentage of profit than &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2013/10/28Apple-Reports-Fourth-Quarter-Results.html&quot;&gt;Apple, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Schmitt1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Nosek, a professor at the University of Virginia and director of the Center for Open Science, says, “Academic publishing is the perfect business model to make a lot of money. You have the producer and consumer as the same person: the researcher. And the researcher has no idea how much anything costs.” Nosek finds this whole system is designed to maximize the amount of profit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, as the researcher, produce the scholarship and I want it to have the biggest impact possible and so what I care about is the prestige of the journal and how many people read it. Once it is finally accepted, since it is so hard to get acceptances, I am so delighted that I will sign anything — send me a form and I will sign it. I have no idea I have signed over my copyright or what implications that has — nor do I care, because it has no impact on me. The reward is the publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nosek further explains why researchers are ever supportive by explaining the dedicated loyal customer base mantra, “What do you mean libraries are canceling subscriptions to this? I need this. Are you trying to undermine my research?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to a steadfast dedication by researchers, the academic publishing market, in its own right, is streamlined, aggressive, and significantly capitalistic. The publishing market is also more diverse than just the face of Elsevier. Johan Rooryck, a professor at Universiteit Leiden, says, “Although Elsevier is the publisher that everybody likes to hate, if you look at Taylor &amp;amp; Francis, Wiley, or Springer they all have the same kind of practices.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heather Morrison, a professor in the School of Information Studies at the University of Ottawa, unpacks the business model behind academic publisher Springer and says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at who owns Springer, these are private equity firms, and they have changed owners about five times in the last decade. Springer was owned by the investment group Candover and Cinven who describe themselves as ‘Europe’s largest buy-out firm.’ These are companies who buy companies to decrease the cost and increase the profits and sell them again in two years. This is to whom we scholars are voluntarily handing our work. Are you going to trust them? This is not the public library of science. This is not your average author voluntarily contributing to the commons. These are people who are in business to make the most profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should a consumer heed Morrison’s rationale and want to look deeper into academic publishers cost structure for themselves one is met with a unique situation: the pricing lists for journals do not exist. “It’s because they negotiate individually with each institution and they often have non-disclosure agreements with those institutions so they can’t bargain with knowing what others paid,” says Martin Eve, founder of the Open Library of the Humanities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to a general lack of pricing indexes, the conversation around the value of a publication is further complicated by long-term career worth. David Sundahl, a senior research fellow at the Clayton Christensen Institute for Disruptive Innovation, says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We actually understand how money passed through to artists who wrote music and authors who wrote books — but it is not clear how the value of a publication in a top tier journal will impact someone’s career. Unlike songs or books where the royalty structure is defined, writing a journal article is not clear and is dependent not on the people who consume the information but rather deans and tenure committees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Schmitt2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Disruption Doable?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is precisely the prior lack of a pricing and value barometer that leads to the complexities associated with disrupting the main players in academic publishing. “Adam Smith’s invisible hand works to lower prices and increase productivity but it can only do so when valuation or pricing is known and the same thing is true for disruption. If you don’t know how to value something, you actually don’t have tiers of a market,” says Sundahl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a disruptive force was to significantly change academic publishing it needs to happen in a market that is currently underserved or undesirable by the large-scale publisher. “Disruptive innovation is usually driven by a group who can’t afford to build something that is as big, fancy and sophisticated as the existing solution — they then have to find a market where either people don’t have anything available to them or they are satisfied with something less than perfect,” says Sundahl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should academic scholarship keep existing in a similar trajectory as in the past decades Sundahl finds incumbents (existing big publishers) almost always win when competition takes place along those sustaining strategy lines. “To revolutionize academic publication, a new system would need to be developed in a basement market which would eventually enable people to gain enough credibility doing this new solution. People would then begin to value this lower end, well done research, and that is when the world starts to change,” says Sundahl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prior is exactly what large entities like the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation or perhaps even top tier research one (R1) universities can’t do. “They have to play the game the way the winners are already playing it. Incumbents almost always win under those conditions,” says Sundahl. And to further complicate matters, junior colleges and community colleges, which perhaps would represent fertile grounds to be served by a newer, “basement market” entrant, may be less likely to spearhead this new outlet themselves due increasing government constraints focused nearly exclusively on job placement and starting salaries in lieu of a research-based, theoretical curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Open Access Packs a Punch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driven by the lopsided power structure the move toward open access and the unrestricted access to academic information has been exponentially growing. Perhaps it is, itself, a “basement market” for leveling the academic publication environment and creating a market where respect and credibility can be fostered, grown and transitioned into the existing academic prestige, merit, and tenure conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The open access environment is one of the more fertile environments for people to be thinking: if we don’t like the old way, what should the new way look like,” says Heather Joseph, executive director at the Scholarly Publishing and Academic Resources Coalition (SPARC). Joseph finds that the quantifiable numbers of open access journals speak for themselves and says, “You can look at the number of strictly open access journals if you look at the Directory of Open Access Journals (DOAJ). When it started tracking open access journals there were a few dozen and now they list over 10,000 open access journals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The push toward open access is not only growing in sheer numbers of journals but also in an increasingly confrontational strategy that academics leverage against large publishers. “At the moment, the Netherlands, the whole country, has said to Elsevier that we want all of our researchers to be able to publish open access in your journals at the same rates we would pay for a subscription last year and if you can’t do that we’re going to cancel every one of your journals, for all of our universities nationwide,” says Eve. “They have a few days left to resolve this, and it looks like they are going to cancel all the Elsevier journals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rooryck found his recent very public decision to step down and move his Elsevier journal Linga to open access met with complete support from the other six editors and 31 editorial board members. “The process went very easily. We were all aware of the pricing and Elsevier’s practices and within a week everyone agreed to resign,” says Rooryck. Eve’s platform, the Open Library of Humanities, will now house the new open access iteration of Lingua, which will be called Glossa. Eve says, “Right away it is 50% cheaper to run it through us then when it was with Elsevier. So anybody subscribing to it already sees 50% more revenue.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rooryck finds the move toward broad open access a natural progression and says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The knowledge we produce as academics and scientists should be publicly available in the same way we have a company that delivers water to our faucets and electricity to our home. These are things we have a right to. Public knowledge and education is a human right and it should not come with a profit tag of 35%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it appears open access has the ability to simultaneously diffuse academic knowledge to a larger body of readers and cut costs significantly, many feel that the for profit academic publishers are still situated to continue into the near future. Joseph says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the play for most smart commercial publishers is to try to preserve the current environment for as long as they can: delay the policy changes, delay the culture changes and to be working on things like tools and services applying to aggregation of data, where they are then embedding themselves more deeply in the workflow of researchers and becoming essential to researchers in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are no longer essential to researchers in the, ‘you have to publish in my journal in order to get tenure and promotion’ what do they replace that with? I think the smart publishing companies like Elsevier, like Springer, who are very smart in that regard, have been thinking about where they can go to be playing a role of continuing to be seen as essential by the research community once they are no longer playing the role of providing assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Onward and Upward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the US Congress we have been finally making &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.sciencemag.org/policy/2015/07/senate-panel-approves-public-access-bill&quot;&gt;progress&lt;/a&gt; with the Fair Access to Science and Technology Research (FASTR) bill. It moved through the committee it was referred to in the Senate and is poised to move out of the Senate and potentially be considered by the House and hopefully pass. Ten years ago, I would have said we didn’t have a chance to do a stand-alone bill,” says Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the recent congressional support Joseph refers to is one more verifying measure that the majority of articles will be moving toward an open and accessible framework. Many in the academic community hope that this government support signals the reprioritization of a research framework and the switching of the guard. And while the prior is extremely important, others in the academic community are hoping to grow “basement markets” from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Center for Open Science, which provides seed funds to startups in the academic scientific research space, is led by Nosek and focuses on aligning scientific values to scientific practices. “The open science framework is just a means at connecting all the research services that researchers use across the entire research life cycle,” says Nosek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nosek is optimistic about the evolution of technology in open science and says, “There are a lot of startups going at different parts of the research life cycle. Whether it is publication and what a publication means, or looking at full articles and whether you can make articles convey information in smaller bite size pieces.” Nosek tells me that there are so many solutions happening in research right now and mentions it is hard to judge what the true solutions will look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sometimes think some of the ideas haven’t a chance, but what do I know? I could be completely wrong about it. And that is the whole point — do some experimentation and try out ideas. And the fact is there are a lot of people who see what the problems are and have a unique sense of a potential solution — it is a very lively time to try out different answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time will tell if open access will be the needed disruption to allow the academic environment to right itself or if a new market emerges from startup incubators like the Center for Open Science. Regardless of how the future vision is realized, most in the academic community hope that the new iteration of scholarly articles and publishing will do more good toward humankind than that of a hefty profit margin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image header credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/ejbsf/8426493938/&quot;&gt;ejbSF&lt;/a&gt;; creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A View From Jerusalem</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/a-view-from-Jerusalem/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/blog/a-view-from-Jerusalem</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An abridged version of a talk by Guy Stroumsa at a conference held in his honour in Jerusalem&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a &lt;em&gt;révolutionnaire manqué&lt;/em&gt;, the comparative study of religions and their cohort of dreams of transformations, of patterns of mutations, both within societies and inside the self, has always represented a deeply subversive activity. I wish to offer here a midrashic reflection of sorts on subversion as an intellectual and moral duty: that of refusing to lie on the Procrustean beds prepared for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last half-century, the Hebrew University has been a true home for me, one which I never really left. A &lt;em&gt;witz&lt;/em&gt; describes psychoanalysts as people whose analysis was not quite successful: they were not able to move ahead. &lt;em&gt;Mutatis mutandis&lt;/em&gt;, the same could be said about professors and their education. The very first day of my new life in Israel, in July 1966 (I was eighteen, as old as the country), was also that of my baptismal day as a student at the Hebrew University – more precisely, at its summer Ulpan: the early stages of my interminable struggle with Hebrew. Like other ambitious universities, the Hebrew University has always known that its first, absolute commitment was to the search of truth and to what it entails: critical thought, moral backbone, intellectual freedom. The intellectual audacity expected from universities is worthless without the civic courage to constantly question thought patterns and attitudes current in their own societies, to affirm, clearly and loudly, their autonomy and independence from the bodies and governments funding them. In Rabelais’ lapidary dictum: “Science sans conscience n’est que ruine de l’âme.” This permanent questioning is, precisely, their duty of subversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, paradoxically, universities are everywhere under threat, asked to ‘be relevant,’ rather than to search for truth, to ‘deliver’ rather than to educate. I say paradoxically, as human societies, despite blatant, shocking inequalities, have never been as affluent as they are today. I cannot analyze this paradox here or even attempt to suggest solutions. I want at least to stress what you all know, that Faculties of Humanities are much more seriously threatened that those of Sciences and vocational schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural sciences have an easier time, I think, in their rebuttal of utilitarian demands, as it is relatively simple for them to show the value of pure research: no applied mathematics or physics without pure mathematics and physics. At least in theory, one can still make an argument about &lt;em&gt;la science pour la science&lt;/em&gt;, as one does about &lt;em&gt;l’art pour l’art&lt;/em&gt;. A similar argument is far less obvious for the humanities. Very soon, one will hear the argument about what the Germans call the &lt;em&gt;kleine Fächer&lt;/em&gt;, the “small fields,” such as, at least in the Israeli context, the paradigmatic Assyriology: too expensive, too few students. And besides, who cares about Assyriology?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem, I fear, is made more complex by the fact that the humanities, the &lt;em&gt;Geisteswissenschaften&lt;/em&gt;, in their wish to be taken seriously, have calqued themselves on the &lt;em&gt;Naturwissenschaften&lt;/em&gt;. They are still doing that, as shown by the latest fad, “digital humanities,” and by the widely spread tendency to value only what can be quantified. I am all for the use of modern technologies in the service of the humanities, but at the moment, the technologies seem to take over the fields rather than serve them. Faculties of Humanities risk forgetting that their task, beyond producing new knowledge, also consists in offering a reflection on knowledge, on its conditions, its limits and its meaning. Such a second-order reflection is essentially subversive, as it questions the natural acceptance of existing conditions for the reproduction of knowledge in society, including in its educational institutions, and in the political system sustaining them. The humanities are deeply unsettling, and therefore, in this age of increasing resistance to questioning, increasingly unfashionable. By historicizing and relativizing all ideas and world-views, they disturb what is held sacred in all quarters. It is, then, by nature that the humanities, more than any other branch of knowledge in the universities, are subversive. I would go further, and argue that it is only by recognizing and embracing the subversive nature of their craft that humanists can avoid the new, deeply threatening &lt;em&gt;trahison des clercs&lt;/em&gt;, to borrow the title of Julien Benda’s famous pamphlet, toward which the market forces of the global village almost inexorably push us all. Almost inexorably, but perhaps not quite: if the historian (even the historian of religion) is no prophet, she or he can never be sure that the claim of subversion will only remain a symbolic gesture of protest, done only for honor’s sake. It may also, perchance, hide the seed of a future rebirth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the modern university is a secular place: no theological presupposition, no religious limitation may regulate the questioning of scientists and scholars alike. This, we must reckon, creates a particular problem for the study of religion, a problem that cannot be easily dismissed, although it often goes unrecognized. Creating secular knowledge about the sacred is by no means an obvious task, even when one deals with societies far away from ours in either time or space. Nor is the study of religion, despite appearances, perceived as a problem only by those who have religious leanings, and who may feel that their world, their values, are under attack, perhaps even desecrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have come to realize over the years, creating secular knowledge about the sacred is also felt as a threat by the secularists, those who feel enlightened, free from the prejudices and fears so characteristic (they think) of religion. The modern, comparative study of religion is a study of humans, not of gods. More precisely, it is the study of humans dealing with the gods. It is, therefore, more akin to anthropology than to theology. While the study of religion cannot protect religion from the secular invasion (indeed, it reflects and often represents this invasion), it also refuses to evacuate religion from the secular world. In its double movement, the study of religion thus antagonizes both the proponents of a religious worldview and those of a secular one, appearing to both as a threat. No surprise, then, if it is deeply unfashionable. At the same time, it is urgently needed, as it stands at the very core of Faculties of Humanities, encapsulating, as it were, the duty of subversion that is theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, after the last Paris terrorist massacres, a dear friend of mine from Berlin expressed her shock at the speed with which French politicians were switching to a warlike vocabulary. The reticence to speak of war is easily understandable, and highly commendable, certainly on the side of Germans, who can afford historical amnesia even less than others. My immediate reaction to her remark, however, was that I had never considered the world I lived in to be a peaceful one. From the Qumran scroll describing the eschatological War between the Sons of Light with the Sons of Darkness and Mani’s &lt;em&gt;Sermon of the Great War&lt;/em&gt; to more recent bouts of religious violence, in Jamestown, Waco, Ayodhya, Bali, Beirut, New York, Ankara or Bamako, war has always been omnipresent. We know, moreover, that not all Sons of Darkness belong to the enemy camp; some also sit in our midst. For me, then, humanism is conceivable only in a world at war; it must be a fighting humanism. In his theses &lt;em&gt;On the concept of history&lt;/em&gt;, written in 1940, Walter Benjamin could say: “the emergency situation in which we live is the rule.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ultimi barbarorum!” Spinoza’s cry of rage and despair, which he inscribed on a placard when hearing of the lynching of his friends, the De Witt brothers, in 1672, might have cost him his life, had not his lodger wisely locked him up in his room. “Ultimi barbarorum!” This cry resonates today in this impossible city, Jerusalem. Before the end of my first year of studies at the Hebrew University started the Six Day War – a war still going on, almost fifty years later. A life of learning and of teaching under such conditions is something difficult to grasp, and quite hard to sustain, as no university can remain an island of reason in a sea of madness, of honesty in a situation of injustice, certainly not when it stands, and quite concretely so, at the very seam between conqueror and conquered. We have tried seriously, students and teachers alike, to keep our labs, our libraries and our seminar rooms aseptic, as it were, to concentrate on what we were doing, isolated from the world looming right outside our window. &lt;em&gt;Wissenschaft als Beruf&lt;/em&gt;: we have done our best to take Max Weber’s injunction seriously. We have played by the rules of democracy, while a whole people was, and still is being kept under military occupation, without civil rights, now for almost half a century – deprived of its freedom by those whose children read about Israel’s Exodus from Egypt and the books of the prophets in the original biblical Hebrew! For many among us, this has been at times intolerably stressful, unbearably painful. At some point, the bow must break. Under some circumstances, it is in the mode of protest that the duty of the scholar must be expressed. Cultivating the humanities in such a climate does not necessarily entail the splendid isolation of a (more or less) air-conditioned ivory tower. It can also express a potent protest, represent, as it were, a subversive activity against the reigning order. I have long been impressed by what Raja Shehadeh, a Palestinian writer from Ramallah, has called &lt;em&gt;şumūd&lt;/em&gt;, a noble way of resisting daily brutality and the constant rape of the soul by stubbornly sticking to one’s beliefs, way of life, and ethos. Insisting on remaining oneself, on keeping high one’s torch of values in front of politicians lending their support to thugs, ‘thugs for God’s sake,’ one might call them, and transmitting this torch to the youth: there is a real element of subversion here, perhaps even, who knows, a powerful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are left here with a theologico-political aporia rooted in the very nature of Zionism. Like all movements of national liberation, Zionism achieved its goals, at best, only very partially. Here, the founders of the Hebrew University were quite lucid, aware from the start of the deep-seated ambiguities of the adventure in which they were taking part. I shall mention here only Yehuda Leon Magnes, the first President of the Hebrew University, Martin Buber, the first President of the Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities, and Gershom Scholem, another President of this Academy. In his magnum opus, a biography of the seventeenth-century false messiah Sabbatai Zevi, first published (in Hebrew) in 1959, Scholem could warn of the explosive mixture of old messianic ideas and modern political ideals. Today, the dialectics of the return to Zion threaten to lead to what is perceived, by too many, as Israel’s ‘manifest destiny’: after the Reconquista of the whole land, the segregation into reserves of the Palestinians, or even their eventual expulsion. The supreme jewel in David’s crown, for them, would be the rebuilding of the Jerusalem Temple and, one imagines, the ensuing restoration of daily blood sacrifices (what else would one do in the Temple?), after a pause of a mere two millenia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is certainly important, and tragically fascinating, to study the sinuous paths through which religious tradition and cultural legacy can - and do - degenerate into such lunacy. This urgent task is that of historians of religion. But it is not our only task, nor is it our most immediate one. If we wish to avoid what might soon lead to nothing less than a conflict of world dimensions, we must also fight the present neo-messianic madness urgently, and furiously. When fair is foul, and foul is fair, civic courage meets intellectual duty, and intellectual courage means civic duty. The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, its Faculty of Humanities, and its students of religion, must be at the front line in this subversive war against the murderous folly threatening our society and our humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text: &amp;#39;Concluding Remarks&amp;#39; to &amp;#39;Upholding Scripture, Rejecting Scripture: Strategies of Religious Subversion: a Conference Celebrating the Work of Guy G. Stroumsa&amp;#39;, Hebrew University of Jerusalem and Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities, Jerusalem, 4-5 January 2016; read at the Israel Academy, 5 January 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header Image: &amp;#39;Coexist Jerusalem: Tunnel near Gaza Street, Jerusalem&amp;#39; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/zeevveez/2573448048/&quot;&gt;zeevveez&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
